Guide to the New-York Historical Society Ephemera Record Group 1839-2019 NYHS-RG 14
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Ephemera Scrapbooks, 1849-1985; 2.5 Linear feet in 6 document boxes and one oversize folder.
  External organizations represented in the ephemera scrapbooks, many of which held meetings and other events onsite, or collaborated with N-YHS on exhibitions or other programming: Modjeska Club, American Jewish Historical Society, Ukrainian Academy of Arts and Sciences, Municipal Art Society, Railway and Locomotive Historical Society, National Sculpture Society, Netherlands Aid Society, Polish Institute of Art and Sciences, United Daughters of the Confederacy, Steamship Historical Society of America, New York Folklore Society, National Council of Jewish Women, Society of Architectural Historians, Society for the Preservation of Long Island Antiquities, and most significantly, Allied Artists of America, who organized annual competitions for exhibitions; the School Art League, who hosted a medal and scholarship presentation; and the New York Society for General Semantics, who offered a popular seminar series at N-YHS.
  The scrapbooks contain a few formats outside the record group's defined parameters for ephemera, chiefly newsletters and press releases.
  The Series II materials were originally collected and compiled by a prior staff member in 10 chronological scrapbooks; the original order was maintained during and after their disassembly and foldering by a conservator in 2015. The container list transcribes the original title assigned to each scrapbook; the original cover and spine appears before each run of files attributed to the respective scrapbook.
  - Scrapbook. Lecture Cards. Volume 1 (6 folders), 1843-1923 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1-6)
    Includes tickets to 1854 semi-centennial celebration dinner at the Metropolitan Hotel; 1860 commemoration of the birthday of Washington Irving; 1903 laying of the corner-stone of the new building (both for platform seating and regular admission); 1905 centennial banquet at Delmonico's (pink ticket for balcony admission, which was designated for female members); 1917 reception and "Father Knickerbocker Pageant;" 1917 series of illustrated lectures for children. Final folder contains index for speaker names.
  - Scrapbook. Lecture Cards. Volume 2 (6 folders), 1924-1949 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 7-12)
    Includes musical lectures and recital handouts; 1941 Christmas program. Final folder contains index for speaker names.
  - Scrapbook. Tickets. Volume 3 (4 folders), 1943-1976 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 1-4)
  - Scrapbook. Exhibition Cards, 1909-1942 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 13)
    Includes announcements for exhibitions. Scrapbook spine also includes labels for "Miscellaneous Cards" and "Gold Medal for Achievement in History" materials, but these were not present in the scrapbook.
  - Scrapbook. Special Events (7 folders), 1939-1951 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 1-7)
    Includes programs, tickets, order forms, and calendars for musical programming, special and press previews, exhibitions, symposia, and other special events. Special items of note include materials from the fight to preserve the Aquarium in Battery Park and the Thompson Homestead Memorial museum briefly operated by N-YHS.
  - Scrapbook. Special Events. Posters, 1939-1951 (Box OS-1, Folder 2)
    Poster for special exhibition "Our City Hall in History" (October 1949-Feburary 1950) and posters for undated "How Early America Lived" demonstration for American history students on the operation of early household inventions.
  - Scrapbook. Special Events (3 folders), 1951-1963 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 8-10)
    Includes programs, handouts, invitations, and chiefly calendars (see also: oversize folder of Series I).
  - Scrapbook. Tickets (8 folders), 1963-1971 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1-8)
    Includes programs, calendars, and invitations in addition to tickets.
  - Scrapbook. N-YHS Exhibition Brochures, Calendar of Events, Stationery, Gazettes, etc. (7 folders), 1971-1982 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1-7)
    Contents are true to titles. Many materials have come loose from the scrapbook pages and are housed in sleeves.
  - Scrapbook. N-YHS Exhibition Brochures, Calendar of Events, Stationery, Gazettes, etc (2 folders), 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 1-2)
    Contents are true to title. Materials have been removed from plastic sleeves and placed in paper slings to retain semblance of original placement.
  - Scrapbook. Promotional Publications (4 folders), 1983-1985 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 3-6)